Russell E. Miller Papers MS117
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Russell E. Miller Papers
1852 -- 1993
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Miller, Russell E.
MS117
1.25 Linear Feet
2 Volumes
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into one series.
Biographical / Historical
Russell Elliott Miller was a Professor of History, University Historian and Archivist of Tufts University, and author of "Light on the Hill, A History of Tufts College from 1852 to 1952" and the second volume "Light on the Hill, A History of Tufts University since 1952." He was born in Bloomington, Minnesota, on April 25, 1916, to one of the last pioneer families in the Minnesota prairie. His mother spoke Dakota Sioux, which she had learned as a child. He received a B.A. in Education in 1937 and an M.A. in political science in 1939, both from the University of Florida at Gainesville. From 1942 to 1946, he served in the Army Air Corps as an enlisted man, rising to the rank of technical sergeant. Initially with personnel and classification, he was finally assigned to the historical section (intelligence) at the headquarters of the troop carrier command. In 1948 he earned a Master of Arts in history from Princeton University and came to Tufts that same year.
In 1952 he received a PhD from Princeton, and in 1964 Tufts appointed him Professor of History and University Historian and archivist. He taught courses ranging from the history of western civilization to the history of the American frontier. In 1966, he published "Light on the Hill, A History of Tufts College from 1852 to 1952." That year he received the Distinguished Service Award from the Tufts Alumni Association and became an honorary member of Phi Beta Kappa. In 1975 he became the Walter S. Dickson Professor of English and American History and chaired the Department of History from then until 1980. He was voted Emeritus Professor of English and American History in 1981 and received an honorary Doctor of Letters degree in 1983. In 1986, he completed the second volume of Tufts history, "Light on the Hill II, A History of Tufts University since 1952."
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the typescript of Russell Miller's "Light on a Hill: A History of Tufts College from 1852 to 1952" in addition to correspondence, notes, and publicity about the book. It also includes one file of correspondence on the second volume of "Light on the Hill," called "Light on the Hill II, A History of Tufts University since 1952."
In addition to papers relating to "Light on the Hill," the Russell Miller collection also includes two folders regarding his academic career and life, advancement records, and one box of clippings and unidentified written histories of Tufts that Miller used in his research on the university's history. In particular, one folder in this box contains images and clippings from Tufts' opening in 1853.
University history
- Russell Miller papers, 1852 -- 1993; 1853 -- 1986; MS117.001; 1.25 Linear Feet; 2 Volumes
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the typescript of Russell Miller's "Light on a Hill: A History of Tufts College from 1852 to 1952" in addition to correspondence, notes, and publicity about the book. It also includes one file of correspondence on the second volume of "Light on the Hill," called "Light on the Hill II, A History of Tufts University since 1952."
  In addition to papers relating to "Light on the Hill," the Russell Miller collection also includes two folders regarding his academic career and life, advancement records, and one box of clippings and unidentified written histories of Tufts that Miller used in his research on the university's history. In particular, one folder in this box contains images and clippings from Tufts' opening in 1853.
  Arrangement
  The typescripts are arranged by chapter, unpublished histories are arranged as found.
  Conditions Governing Access
  75 years from the date of creation. Open for research.
  - Light on the Hill, general, MS117.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
    Open for research.
  - Light on the Hill, Introduction, MS117.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
  - Light on the Hill, Chapter 1, MS117.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
  - Light on the Hill, Chapter 2, MS117.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
  - Light on the Hill, Chapter 3, MS117.001.001.00005 (Box 1)
  - Light on the Hill, Chapter 4, MS117.001.001.00006 (Box 1)
  - Light on the Hill, Chapter 5, MS117.001.001.00007 (Box 1)
  - Light on the Hill, Chapter 6, MS117.001.001.00008 (Box 1)
  - Light on the Hill, Chapter 7, MS117.001.001.00009 (Box 1)
  - Light on the Hill, Chapter 8, MS117.001.001.00010 (Box 1)
  - Light on the Hill, Chapter 9, MS117.001.001.00011 (Box 1)
  - Light on the Hill, Chapter 10, MS117.001.001.00012 (Box 1)
  - Light on the Hill, Chapter 11, MS117.001.001.00013 (Box 1)
  - Light on the Hill, Chapter 12, MS117.001.001.00014 (Box 1)
  - Light on the Hill, Chapter 13, MS117.001.002.00001 (Box 2)
  - Light on the Hill, Chapter 14, MS117.001.002.00002 (Box 2)
  - Light on the Hill, Chapter 15, MS117.001.002.00003 (Box 2)
  - Light on the Hill, Chapter 16, MS117.001.002.00004 (Box 2)
  - Light on the Hill, Epilogue, MS117.001.002.00005 (Box 2)
  - Light on the Hill, photo proofs and notes, MS117.001.002.00006 (Box 2)
  - Light on the Hill, publicity, MS117.001.002.00007 (Box 2)
  - Light on the Hill, Volume 2, correspondence, MS117.001.002.00008 (Box 2)
  - Light on the Hill, Volume 2, advertising, MS117.001.002.00009 (Box 2)
  - Clippings and unpublished histories of Tufts, 1897 -- 1978; MS117.001.003.00001 (Box 3)
  - Clippings and unpublished histories of Tufts, 1908 -- 1961; MS117.001.003.00002 (Box 3)
  - Clippings and images of Tufts' opening and dedication, 1853 -- 1857; MS117.001.003.00003 (Box 3)
  - Clippings and images of Tufts' opening and dedication, 1853 -- 1857; MS117.001.003.00004 (Box 3)
  - Russell E. Miller vertical file, 1 of 2, 1948 -- 1993; MS117.001.003.00005 (Box 3)
  - Russell E. Miller vertical file, 2 of 2, 1983 -- 1993; MS117.001.003.00006 (Box 3)
    75 years from the date of creation.
  - Light on the Hill: A History of Tufts College, 1852 -- 1952; MS117.001.004 (Box 4)
  - A Light on the Hill Vol. II: A History of Tufts University Since 1952, MS117.001.005 (Box 5)